Thanks to inviting me
for the talk today.
And I'll be just talking
about transformers
for music and
audio, which is very
different than what all of this
were doing this past course.
I'm also the only
speaker from Stanford.
So I have to do a good job.
So you can see very
good slides because I'm
kind of representing the
University in some sense.
So yeah, so the flow
of the talk today
is basically like I'll be
throwing a lot of stuff.
It's kind of like a
buffet style and then
you feel free to like or
dislike whatever you want.
And I'll be talking mostly
about three papers of what I've
been working on and start with
introducing what transformers
are from a different
perspective, what
audio representations are,
talk about generative model
for audio, which is
just doing like language
modeling on the sample level.
Then I'll talk about how can one
do language modeling for speech
and audio which is
different than what
people do for text, what
are the current trends
in the literature.
Finally, I'll briefly
mention similar stuff
as to what was happening in
computer vision with regard
to vision transformers, what can
we adopt similar ideas for all
your transformers and throw
in a bit of signal processing
to improve the performance.
I've been told that the talk
is about 35 to 40 minutes
with about 15 minutes
of Q&A. I should also
say that all of the
opinions are mine
and Stanford or
any other professor
is not responsible for any
of the mistake which I do.
So transformers have
kind of revolutionized
in the way everyone was
approaching deep learning.
Before that, it
was all about CNNs.
And mostly all of
these prominent models
have been coming in waves.
So there was a time
when everyone was just
applying CNNs.
Then came a time
where people started
adopting CNNs and some sort
of derivative contributions
and slowly the
recurrent networks
were getting out of fashion.
Now it seems like transformers
are in fashion all the time.
So it seems to be solving almost
every single problem which
is being thrown at them.
So what's special
about transformers?
One of the fact that struck
me was their simplicity which
is if you think about it--
and it has been
hugely popular also.
So it was just released in
2018 and within three years,
it has about 30,000
citations and it
is kind of solving every single
problem in every single domain.
It has its limitations
though, also.
But if you think
about it, in a way,
transformers are
basically like a way
of just cascading self-attention
with feature learning.
And if we keep on doing
it over and over again,
then the model in a way learns
which parts of the input
are important and keep on
transforming them, removing
the content which
are not important,
and just have the
limited information which
is just responsible
for a particular task.
And it has been
very, very difficult
to keep up with the literature.
I have put it as a
joke here, but then
even Twitter's
recommendation engine would
kind of just getting out of--
they were getting haywire as
to why is Chris Manning just
searching over transformers.
And that was way back in 2020.
So it has been difficult
for researchers
also to keep up with the
pace of what's going on.
Just before transformers,
all of the NLP community
was just going gaga
about bidirectional LSTMs
with attention.
So every single
paper before 2017
was just like you have
encoder and LSTM layers.
You keep on adding
multiple layers.
And then after that, you
have attention mechanism
which just learns
at what's important
and then just keeps on decoding
sequentially one at a time.
But this was not kind of
like an ideal way to do it
because what turns out is
when we start throwing longer
sequences, the
connections are no longer
storing the gradient updates
in a way it should be doing.
So what the researchers
from Google said--
instead of having
just a attention layer
at the very last encoding, we
would just have these attention
mechanisms at every single
layer which, in a way,
would just learn what's
important for a particular
problem at that
particular layer and we
keep on doing it
over and over again.
So then the whole idea of
transformers and attention
mechanism cascaded one
after the other came.
And I love going to the
details because this is
the last class of the course.
But then usual
tricks do help across
the neural net
literature which is
like having
multi-head attentions,
having skip connection
and layer norms.
So all of these things,
they are not only
getting gains for
transformers themselves,
but they can be just applied to
any single other architecture
also.
The other thing which
is helping this research
is basically the compute power
is getting better and better.
So all of these big
companies are just
throwing massive amounts
of computing resources
at solving very, very
simple and trivial tasks.
The top of the hill being
the switch transformer
which was discussed
in the course also.
But one of the thing which I
think started all of this trend
was ELMo, which
was just learning
these contextualized
representations
for natural language processing.
And that model right
here was perhaps one
of the first kind of
model 1.0 or something
or 1.1 in terms of
bringing and ushering
in the whole revolution.
You can see how similar these
kinds of models look like.
BERT was basically
like inspired heavily
from ELMo in which they just
replaced one of the LSTM layers
with transformer models.
So a point to note
also is irrespective
of natural language
processing or other domain,
these can be adopted in
a variety of domains.
And for today's talk, I'll be
just adopting them to audio.
So I basically start
with introducing
people what audio
representations are
and just for the
sake of completeness
talk about spectrograms.
So you can take any
time domain signal
and you can
decompose that signal
into a variety of
business functions.
And if you take up
a Fourier transform,
you're kind of like decomposing
the actual time domain
signal into its sinusoidal
pieces components.
So if you have a
waveform here like this,
which is a sum of
three pure sinusoids,
then their sum
basically is this.
And you can see that
when you take a Fourier
transform and its
magnitude, you kind of
have their strength of the
individual components shown
here.
So you can take
another waveform, let's
say a square wave, and what you
have is basically much richer
sinusoidal decomposition
because it is
kind of a discontinuous signal.
So you need many more
sinusoids to represent
that particular signal as
close to the actual signal
as possible.
And here also you can see that--
OK, if this was a
square wave, then
it is actually made up
of a lot of sinusoids
where each of the bar here
represents the strength
of the particular sinusoid.
From an optimization
perspective, I mean,
this right away is
suboptimal, right,
because you're kind of fixing
up the number of sinusoids
you are using for
representing a square wave.
I would have rather
used a basis function
which was a square wave itself
than a sinusoidal signal,
right?
The second thing
is like even if you
are taking a sinusoid signal,
we kind of are just putting them
in a equidistant space.
So you are kind of dividing
the whole frequency
axis into equidistant bends.
And each of the
bends are responsible
for like a particular
sinusoid a lot.
So that is like a traditional
Fourier representation
for representing any signal.
What are spectrograms?
But in reality, all of these
signals are discontinuous.
All of these signals
vary quite a bit, right?
So you can have a
signal while I'm
speaking which is like a square
wave for a certain period
of time and then
it gets sinusoidal
and then it becomes
something else.
So what we really
need is in a way
to kind of take batches
of the input signal
and take Fourier transform
of these individual batches.
I'm deliberately using
the word batches,
but you can like--
in traditional terms,
you're windowing the signal.
So right here, you can see that
you have a continuous signal,
you keep on windowing it, you
apply the Fourier transform,
and what you get is
basically like a spectrogram
representation of the signal.
So right here, what
you're seeing basically
is with each of the slices,
the signal kind of looked
like this after taking
the Fourier transform
with the waveform,
which is there below.
And what you do is for
spectrogram representation,
you keep on stacking these
Fourier transform slides,
the magnitude of the
Fourier transform slices.
And in this way, you kind of
get like a 2D representation
of audio segments.
And if you're coming
from a vision background,
it is basically all
of the things which
you are doing in vision
would just work well
if you just apply them to these
2D spectral representations.
I'll quickly play
how the spectrograms
look like for a wide area
of like common sounds.
So you could see like
for spectrograms you
have kind of like a time
axis on your x-axis.
And then, you have a
frequency axis on y-axis.
And then, for whatever is
your signal of interest,
you're basically putting
these slices together,
and different sound gives
you different spectral
representation.
So it's kind of a vision
problem just in this sort
of like Fourier space.
So there can be different
kinds of representations also.
So one, you could just take
these slices of Fourier
transform and then do like
a linear mapping to them
so that you are kind of
in a way making these
as close to how humans hear.
So you can have a
log of the frequency
and the y-axis and sort
of common frequency.
And then, you get a constant
Q-like representation.
The advantage of
this being you can
see that for
different frequencies,
the spacing in
between the harmonics
kind of remains the same.
So if you are creating
unusual filters,
then that's of a huge
advantage because the signal--
one component of the
invariance is gone,
and you can just learn
these filters, which
are catching on to these
constant templates of Fourier
slices.
You can have Mel
filterbank coefficients,
or you can have the
raw waveform also.
For raw waveforms,
basically there
are two things which we
have to keep in mind.
One is the sampling rate.
So we kind of take
the continuous signal,
and then we discretize
the continuous signal.
So one parameter is how
fast we are sampling
the continuous signal,
so that's typically
on the order of like 16,000
or 8,000 times a second
if you're on telephonic speech.
The other thing which we
also have is how many levels
we are dividing
your vertical axis.
So in this case, you can
see that each of the dots
is basically one level.
And typically, people
use 8-bit quantizers
or 16-bit quantizers.
So in a way, you can think
about that for every one
second of audio
which we would hear,
you would have 16,000 samples.
And then each of
the 16,000 samples
are allowed to take one of
the levels between 0 to 255.
If I can take the problem of
like continuous audio and just
have it in terms of this
sort of discrete space,
then basically I'm just
going to the territory
of doing language modeling.
In my first paper,
so I discussed this,
how can we do
generative modeling
for raw audio, which is similar
to wavenets using transformers.
I'll be putting QR codes.
If you like the
stuff what I'm doing,
and if you think that
this is relevant to you,
please cite or please have a
look in terms of the QR codes,
so, yeah.
So I'll start with the first
subtopic of today's talk,
which is what are
wavenets and how
do we do like this generative
modeling with raw audio?
So in single word, you
can think about this
as doing like language modeling,
or these 255 states of audio.
So you can throw on your
favorite transformer
like Transformer-XL or GPT or
whatever you want to call it.
And just treat the
problem as if you're
trying to predict what are
the levels that are 255.
And you have to predict the next
level given a certain context.
That's what Wavenet was doing.
So the way you are modeling
the probability distribution
of continuous space
is basically you're
trying to predict what's the
probability of the next sample
given some sparse context.
And Wavenet has
been hugely popular
because it has over
3,000 citations.
And it has been a core building
block for almost all speech
and audio related problems.
You can think about
speech to text or text
to speech synthesis, instrument
conversion, packet loss
concealment of internet
speech denoising.
So wherever there is some sort
of element of modifying audio,
people have been using Wavenet
as a core building block.
And raw waveform synthesis
has been difficult
because just the magnitude
of the problem, if I'm just
trying to synthesize
10 seconds of audio
would just amount to like
me having a probability
distribution over
160,000 samples.
And I could tell this stuff
because our ears are very, very
sensitive to subtle changes.
If I'm off by one
pixel in an image--
the image, like
my eyes would not
be as susceptible to noticing
that effect versus if I'm
off by, say, a few
samples in an audio,
it will just catch our
ears pretty quickly.
People have been trying
raw audio synthesis a lot
in the past.
And before all of the
internet and transformer based
approaches kind of like
WaveRNNs and Sample RNNs
were kind of like state
of the art models.
On the right I've shown
a Sample RNN model
which kind of like models
the probability distribution
of what's going to
come next, given
the past at multiple levels.
And this was well done
by Yoshua Bengio at Mila.
But you can closely see.
If you just see
this architecture
versus a transformer
architecture, in a way,
these are starting to
get very, very similar,
because what you're trying to
do is that for the probability
distribution here,
you're trying to see
a lot of local substructures.
And then you keep on doing
it over and over again.
And you can draw parallels,
like, OK, attention mechanism
should also kind of be
doing the same thing.
So this was the kind of
the literature in the past.
What we tried to do was we
just had the WaveNet model
and we tried to see whether
transformers can beat them.
And our intuition was it
should be able to beat them,
because they are successful
all over the other domains,
like in language modeling.
So it should-- it should do
that for raw waveforms also.
We also try to see whether
we can circumvent the order n
constraint by conditioning
on the context itself.
And we did not go for
specific applications.
And we just said, OK, it just
looks like modeling behavior.
How will they do?
So the data set for this was
just like real-world piano
recordings.
So actual sound
should not matter,
because the model is agnostic
to what it is being thrown in.
And the setup was
exactly the same.
You are given a certain
context and have
to predict the next sample.
You do the same
thing with WaveNet.
You do the exact same thing
with transformer-based GPT
kind of a model and
see how well they do.
I'll briefly chat about
what WaveNet models are.
So WaveNet was kind
of like a convolution
based model which
was getting rid
of like all of the
vanishing gradient problem
by just creating a sequential
problem as being learned
by a convolutional model.
So what they did
was basically have
these sort of dilation layers
or a convolution with dilations,
which is basically I kind of
skip in every subsequent layer
by one sample.
So you can see if I have
a dilation factor of 2
with a kernel size of 2, I would
get this kind of a topology,
where my convolution filters
in the very first layer
are just combining
the first two samples.
Then I skip by one
in the next layer.
And then I skip
by three, which is
I look at like the fourth one
in the next layer, and so on.
The loss is still the same.
So I have this network.
I learn a latent space.
And then I have a cross in--
categorical cross entropy
loss, which is basically I
have to predict the next sample
given the previous one.
And I just do the exact same
thing with transformers, also.
But then I have to
make sure that I do it
in a causal manner.
So I have something
which is very
similar to GPT, in which I have
causal masks in my attention
mechanism.
And I keep doing it
over and over again.
So you have self-attention.
After that, you have
feed forward layers.
You just have a stack of
these transformer blocks
and see how would they do.
So I said intuitively
it should work.
It should be doing better than
our base WaveNet models, right?
Because if you look
at the topology,
we are kind of defining a
topology on our ow, right?
So what if the current
prediction at say, layer one
were to depend on very way
back samples, say, instead
of the second sample,
the 10th sample.
So we are kind of ignoring
all of that topology which
would have been important
for a prediction
of this particular task.
Whereas, our transformers with
the self-attention mechanism
can just learn, OK, which part
of the samples are important
and which are not.
And you can keep on
doing it iteratively.
So it made sense to us
that, OK, transform layer
should be doing way better
than WaveNet models.
The second thing which we
came across was like, OK,
we cannot have a lot of context.
For example, the
attention mechanism
needs to store all of
those of order n squares.
In this case, if I'm storing
data at 100 milliseconds,
then I have about 1,600 samples.
And I need to store 1,600
by 1,600 at multiple layers.
And it just becomes
a huge problem
with the data, problem
with the memory constraint.
So what we said was, OK, what if
we just use the context itself
as a latent code?
So in order to have much better
representation at every layer,
we cannot have the huge,
big attention matrices.
So what we said
was we would just
do sample-wise conditioning,
and through our CNN layers
just to understand what
the latent code would be.
So you still have an
attention mechanism or just
a past context.
But then I'm also
conditioning at every sample,
OK, what the next sample should
be given on-the-spot context
embedding.
And if you think
about it, in a way,
it is like, OK, if there are
five or six notes being played
in a piano, then
I'm kind of certain
which notes will be
played to a certain extent
if I just throw in a CNN layer.
So I'll use that
information along with what
my transformers are learning.
And then I would condition it.
And I would just use that
to predict the next sample.
So for the evaluation
criteria, we
did not look for negative
log likelihood scores.
We just looked at how well
our prediction task was.
So we took a stacked
WaveNet, which
was implemented by
DeepMind and saw that, OK,
what was the performance
using their benchmarks,
and even bigger
stacked WaveNets.
We then took--
started to increase
the complexity of
transformers and started
to see whatever we had proposed
in terms of conditioning
on the vanilla
transformer architectures
to see how well they do.
We did not look for an
application specific problem,
which is basically like--
we don't look at how well
perceptual tasks are for,
like, say, text-to-speech
synthesis or speech denoising.
We just look at,
OK, if we are trying
to model this using
a cross entropy loss,
then with the same
model with the same loss
function, how well they do on
similar kind of parameters?
So this was the first
kind of sub-block
of how can we use transformers
for generative modeling.
For the second problem,
I'll do a quick headaway
on how can we use
transformers for doing
language modeling, which
is kind of becoming
a really fancy term right now.
And this work was done by
Julius Smith way back in 2020.
And the goal of this was
can we kind of, in a way,
do language modeling with
continuous audio sequences.
And I briefly mentioned
about that in this part of--
in this sub-block of the talk.
And this is in regard for
solving acoustic scene
understanding.
Which is basically if I'm
given a chunk of audio,
then I want to understand
what's in there.
And if we could do that
well, then, in a way,
we can do a lot of
fancy, nice applications.
So for example, if you think
about self-driving cars.
So Waymo has started to
incorporate microphones
into their self-driving cars.
Why?
Because say, if there
is an ambulance coming,
or if there is a
fire truck coming,
then that sound would be
picked up way, way before even
than lidars or
even their sensors.
So we want to understand
that and take actions
based upon that.
Apple, during COVID, did
a handwashing detection
on their Apple Watch.
Because if you could detect when
someone is washing their hands,
then you can, in
a way, tell people
that you need to wash
hands for 20 seconds.
And then that can be built
upon as a cool application.
It can be used for
music recommendations.
So Spotify, YouTube
Music, kind of
gives very, very
good songs which
you are listening to which
are similar in content
that you would perhaps like.
It can also give really
cool applications, say,
people have tried detecting
depression from audio.
Or I could detect whether
I'm coughing or not,
or I'm sneezing
or not, and these
can be good medical device--
medical applications which
can be used along with the
current diagnosis what doctor
provides.
So the question was
basically, for us,
was how can we do
language modeling
in a continuous audio domain.
And secondly, how
can we train models?
Or how should we
approach doing this?
So this kind of recipe has
become very, very popular
these days in terms of how
would you approach this problem.
It started with openAI
and, to a certain extent,
DeepMind proposing that
in terms of VQ-VAE models.
But it turns out
transformers love operating
in discrete spaces as of now.
And what they kind of do is as
long as your representations
are discrete, they
are very, very good
at modeling what's
going to come next.
So what people
have been proposing
as a workaround is you could
take up your favorite embedding
in some manner.
You could take VQ-VAE embeddings
or you could take a wav2vec.
Or in terms of video, you can
just do classic VGG or ResNet
embeddings.
You can apply K means
clustering to it.
And K means clustering would
give you the discrete codes.
You do language modeling
on those discrete codes.
And you predict the next code.
And in a way, if
you're doing this,
then you're kind of doing
language modeling for audio.
And if you need to
get back to the audio,
then you already
saw with WaveNet
that you can condition
the WaveNet model to give
continuous output.
So you can use those
codes to get back
to the audio similar to
what jukebox and openAI did.
So I'll quickly mention about
what vector quantization is.
It's one of the most
underutilized algorithms,
to be honest.
And what it does
is basically gives,
in a way, discrete codes to
continuous embedding spaces.
So how does it do it?
So you basically have
an embedding space,
let's say, in 2D right here.
You define what are
the number of clusters
you want to put each of them in.
You run k means.
And you would certainly
get these patches
of where all of
these embeddings,
or what would be the
representative embedding
of a continuous embedding.
You can take all
of those patches.
And you can see-- you
can just number them,
or you can just like list them.
So in this case, you can perhaps
have 25 numbers or 20 numbers,
which are, in a way, mapping
from a continuous embedding
to a discrete token.
This is another
example right here.
So in our case,
what we did was we
took patches of spectrogram,
which are basically very small
patches across time
and then shared all
across the frequency axis.
You take those patches, you
learn embedding representation.
In our case, it was just
three-layer autoencoder
fully connected encoders
with three layers of decoders
and have a bottleneck
layer in between.
So that bottleneck
layer, basically,
is kind of similar to
this kind of diagram
in 64 dimensional space
or 128 dimensional space.
You take up those
bottleneck codes.
And then you run K
means clustering on it.
Suddenly, you-- in a way,
you can find discrete codes
for continuous embedding spaces,
or even continuous signals.
And since we know
that transformers kind
of love operating
in discrete spaces,
you can just apply
language modeling now.
And then you can
see what you can do.
So in our case, we just had
very simple, three-layer
fully connected
autoencoder, small patches.
The number of
codes is important.
Because if you have
too many codes,
then you are kind
of just throwing
in all kinds of noisy things.
I'll give an example of
why the number of codes
are important through
some examples.
And you have too
little codes, what
you're doing is you're removing
all of the information which
was relevant.
And you're just kind of
averaging them all out.
I'd start with--
so this idea first
was proposed by jukebox,
which did it for music.
So you do the exact same
thing what I talked about
in a slightly different
manner, in a way that, OK,
you cannot learn codes
for longer sequences.
So you, in a way,
learn sequences
which are just moving
slowly and which
are looking at only a
certain amount of audio.
So we kind of encode this
at these discrete levels,
which are basically like--
all of these,
basically, are codes.
So at every point, I
define, OK, this audio
had, perhaps, code number 55.
And in the next level,
perhaps, it had code number 2.
And the very top, perhaps
it had code number 2,000.
So in a way, I'm
discretizing the whole codes.
Now, what I do is I take up
my favorite transform model,
perhaps a causal
autoregressive one,
and I say that, OK,
given these codes,
try to predict what
codes would come next.
And for sure,
transformers can do that.
So I would generate the
codes in the future.
Once I've generated the
codes in the future,
I can say that, OK,
this problem now
is kind of like a
text-to-speech problem, right?
Because I have this
discrete codes.
Text to speech, in a way, is
going from discrete letters
to continuous audio.
So I would throw in the
fanciest, which was WaveNet,
I would just get back the code.
And I would get the
generated audio.
So this was, in a
way, what I described.
That they take up
a continuous audio.
They have these compressed
codes which they encode
using a CNN in this case.
The method doesn't matter.
You can throw in
the fancier stuff,
like embedding or
latent representation
on those continuous code.
You generate the
patterns, which are
what's going to happen
next in the future.
And then you decode back
using a fancy WaveNet
or state-of-the-art model.
So this was what we were
doing for music synthesis.
What we said was--
yeah, this is good.
This can generate
good amount of music.
But what-- can
these models be used
for generating
good representation
of the current audio?
And the goal there was
can language models
learn representation
which can just
encapsulate whatever we are kind
of giving as an input signal?
So in this case, what we
tried after that was kind of--
you kind of do exactly
kind of similar ideas.
But instead of doing on VA-VAE
end-to-end learned encodings,
we just applied vanilla K means
clustering similar to what
I described earlier.
If you do on
spectrogram patches,
so you take up these
spectrograms of audio.
And you just divide them
into very small chunks,
learn autoencoder encodings
for each of those chunks,
run K means clustering.
In this case, let's say,
I'm learning 16 codes,
represent the continuous audio
in terms of the 16 codes,
have a transformer which can
perhaps predict the next code.
And if I keep on getting better
and better at predicting what's
going to happen next,
then in this linear layer,
I should be encapsulating
what's important
or what's a good summary of
what has happened in the past.
So that was kind of our
intuition behind trying this.
And as I explained,
the number of codes
play a very important role.
You can see here, these are just
two piano notes switching one
after the other.
If I just have 16
number of codes,
it just happens to
have just a single line
of encoding, a single code
assigned to all of this.
Whereas, if I'm
assigning more codes,
then it becomes kind of like
a fine-grained prediction,
where I'm actually able to get
what the individual notes are.
Recently, Facebook also
said, OK, they just
had a different name to
the whole thing, which
is we can just call this
as TextLess NLP also.
In the sense that,
OK, you can do an LP
without having access to text.
But the idea is
very, very similar.
You have an encoder, which is
exactly similar to, say, what
openAPI was using, we
have a VQ-VAE, wav2vec,
or whatever you want to do.
You can apply K means
clustering to it.
We apply language models to it.
And instead of a
decoder in WaveNet,
they just have a
decoder which is
a different version of
text to speech, which
is like Tacotron in this case.
So as you can see,
these are all same wine
in very different bottles.
But the core idea is
almost exactly the same.
So this was like-- it created
a huge uproar of like,
oh, this is going to change NLP.
But this is very, very
similar to what people
have been doing in the past.
So I've already
explained what this was.
So in our case, we
just try to predict
what's going to happen next
given the previous context
and use that
representation similar
to every single one-shot
learning or zero-shot
learning based method.
I also explain why the number
of codes are important.
If you are too
small, then you're
just throwing up a
lot of information.
If you have too large,
then you don't put in--
it is no longer robust to noise.
So this was our setup.
And before I jump
in, I should add
one of the tweets
which I saw from one
of the most
prominent researchers
at DeepMind, which is
basically a lot of times,
it is very, very easy
to bump up numbers.
I can have these details just
not present in my paper, which
actually helps a lot in terms
of improving the performance.
And kind of sometimes
don't take into account
what the actual model
is incorporating
or what model is
contributing versus what
the actual these tricks for
training are incorporating.
So for most of these methods,
what we try to see is we
try to keep almost exactly
the same approach, no data
augmentation, no
fancy label smoothing
or moving average of weights
or decay or whatever.
You just have
similar based recipes
to see how well we are doing.
For this case, the
goal was to say
that how well our models do
with respect to this purely
supervised approach,
and how well it
does with respect to a
similar unsupervised approach.
So in the first case, the
model and all of the weights
have access to all of
the labels, which is
shown just as VGG supervised.
Which is basically you take
up an audio understanding data
set.
And you see how well you are
doing on accuracy metrics.
So that was the first one.
And the second one,
we applied SimCLR,
which was proposed by Geoff
Hinton in which you can take up
these multiple augmentations
of the same input.
You can have patches removed.
You can blur the signal.
You can flip the signal.
You learn embedding
onto the last layer
without access to the
labels, and then just
have a linear head to
predict what's happening.
By using that, we
got a 55% accuracy.
You do the exact same
thing with transformers.
You don't have access to labels.
You just run them while
just predict the next code.
You take the linear layer,
apply the same linear head,
and try to predict
what's happening inside.
And with that, we
got 60% accuracy.
So even though the
results are not good,
but the fact is the
neural networks actually
are very, very good at
getting better and better
with training of
huge amounts of data.
So there's still a 10% gap
between the purely supervised
and purely unsupervised.
But in that, that's
going to improve
with training a lot of
data to these models,
because it doesn't have access
to any label that's present.
So this is a famous paper by
Dan Ellis and Nelson Morgan
at Berkeley, in
which they actually
showed, way back in 1999,
as to why size matters
for deep neural
networks, and also
the number of data
points, which is present.
So as they kept on increasing
the size of the data
set and the
parameters, they kept
on getting lower and
lower error rates.
And this has been true
across any of the data set.
And that's why the
whole excitement
is about unsupervised learning.
So this was, in a way,
a flavor of how can we
do language modeling and
unsupervised learning on audio
for continuous signals.
For the third subplot,
I'll just quickly
mention ideas which are very
similar to what you would have
seen in vision transformers,
but with the caveat that how can
we use some sort of
signal processing
to improve these
performance even further.
So the basic approach still
remains the same exactly
as what you would have seen
in vision transformers.
You have a signal of interest,
which you want to classify.
Here, they are waveform
in sort of images.
The goal is to predict what's
then inside of it, right?
And also, we don't
have any convolutions.
We don't have any other tricks
which we were using before.
All we have to do is they
can-- transformers themselves
solve this particular problem.
So for the data set--
and the whole setup
was still the same.
No data augmentation and no
other forms of these tricks.
You are given 40,000
snippets for training
and 10,000 for validation.
Our job is to predict
as good as possible
as to what's there in the audio.
This problem is very similar
to the sound which you heard
and the video which you saw.
That given this batch,
you are to predict--
given a spectrogram
patch, you have
to predict what's
there inside of it.
We kind of do one step
further than what's
just a simple transform model.
In the sense that
we tried to see
whether some sort of
hierarchy over transform
embeddings would help
us in any manner.
So for that, we used
wavelet decomposition
on the intermediate
transformer embeddings.
So what is a wavelet
decomposition?
In very naive terms,
it can be a way
of decomposing the
intermediate embeddings
into other intermediate
embedding in the sense
that we are kind of
putting these highways
of some embeddings are
moving very slowly,
and some embeddings
are moving very fast,
are retained exactly
at the rate of what the
original signal was.
And why this is important?
Because you can think about that
at every intermediate state,
you are, in a way, learning some
sort of hierarchy in the model.
So if I look at what we do
with the wavelet decomposition
before and after, let's say
you had time across this
and you had the embedding
size across this.
And this whole patch
was your output
of say, the nth layer
of the transformer.
What I say now is,
OK, I would just
have a mapping from this to
the mapping of my interest
using wavelet decomposition, in
which for half of the samples,
I just created the exact
same embedding as what was
known by the transformer model.
In the next half, I would
start combining two at a time.
So in a way, I'm learning this
sort of like a tree structure
within a single layer of
the transformer embedding.
And for now, the wavelet or
the basis function which I use
is simple averaging.
So let's say I have from
all of the embedding
layers in between, I just need
to have one embedding which
is not moving at all, which
is just representative
of whatever is there of the
whole latent space in that nth
layer.
Then in the next layer, I
would just use two at a time.
And then I would
use four at a time.
Then I reach the exact
resolution as what I had.
Doing this operation doesn't
add any parameters whatsoever.
You're just defining what
your basis function would be
or what your wavelet
function would be.
In this case, it
is a Haar wavelet.
And I start combining them.
And I kind of learn a
hierarchy at every single layer
of the transformers.
And this kind of improved our
performance significantly as
compared to not using
them, with addition
of no extra parameters.
And I've come to the
results later also.
So this is how the whole
approach looks like.
You have a frontend.
The frontend is
basically a single layer
of 2,000 neurons followed by
a dense layer of 64 neurons,
which is just to make
sure to conform it
to the intermediate
transformer embeddings.
Let's say if for
the transformers
I define the embedding
size to be 64, then
that's their dimension
which I'm mapping them to.
So I take a broad waveform, I
patch it in very small patches,
similar to how you do
in vision transformers.
I would just have a single
layer of 2,000 neurons followed
by a dense layer of 64
neurons, with the hope
that the first layer kind of
is learning a Fourier basis
function, which
should be adaptable
according to what I'm learning.
After that, I keep on doing
this over and over again.
I don't have a classification
head or anything like that.
I keep on adding multiple stacks
of transformers after that.
And then I have two
approaches of what I
can do in terms of adaptation.
I can do average
pooling across time
of these intermediate
embeddings.
Because that is
very-- the idea is
very similar to what we
do in classical version.
That each of the
embeddings are looking
at much, much broader output
in the subsequent layers.
Or I could do a
wavelet decomposition.
So what I do is that I take
all of these embeddings,
and I define these highways.
So some of the embeddings
are moving fast.
Some of them are
moving very slow.
And some are retained at the
exact same resolution as what
the transformer is learning.
And then I keep doing
this over and over again.
I have a dense layer.
I have my softmax
or sigmoid, whatever
is my classification head.
So this is kind of what
the approach looks like.
We compare it with all of
the traditional vision based
architecture.
So the vision based models
have been very good.
And the performance have been
similar in understanding audio
also.
So we compare all of
those models in terms
of mean average position.
And we see that even the tiniest
models of transformers were
just surpassing all of the
state-of-the-art CNN models.
Which was a very good sign.
Then we started to bump up, OK,
the larger model should keep
on improving the performance.
And with the multiscale
models, as well as with
the pooling layers, they improve
the performance even further,
which was kind of
very surprising to us,
because the number of
parameters are very small.
These are very
tiny architectures,
yet they are surpassing things
like even DenseNet, which
are huge models with a lot
of millions of parameters.
So after that, we said, and
I'm going to conclude quickly,
after that we said that, OK,
this is looking pretty cool.
What actually is the transformer
or the first layer learning
learning, right?
So in order to make
this plot, what we said
was, OK, if you were to take
a classic Fourier transform,
then if my-- this axis is
kind of like frequency.
This axis is the
number of filters,
and this axis is
of the frequency.
Then in a way, it
should be connecting all
of the points in a linear line.
And this is akin to the
number of points in FFT.
So how many points
I'm defining here,
if I'm defining
2,000 points here,
then I would have 2,048
sinusoidal basis functions,
which are going from lower
frequency to the most
highest frequency.
We said, OK, we'll do the
exact same thing, but now
with filters.
So we have a
frequency along y-axis
and the number of
points in my x-axis.
And if it was a classic
Fourier transform, then
it would be connecting
right as a linear line.
But what we did was we
take up the frontend which
is known by transformer,
take its Fourier transform,
sort according to its center
frequency as to what frequency
is activating the most, and
then keep on stacking them.
When we did this
for two problems,
we saw that we are kind of
learning a different time
frequency
representation, which is
specific to a
particular problem.
So if I'm trying to
understand what's there,
the content of the audio
by learned representation,
which is very different than
Fourier transform, which
would have been a
straight line, which
is kind of like a curved
exponential line like this.
And if I do a polyphonic
pitch estimation,
I learn a very
different frontend,
which is adapting to
that particular problem.
So this was very exciting to
us, because making computers
hear in a way in which they're
adapting their ears according
to a particular problem
is a very cool idea.
Second thing is we actually
saw each of the filters
as to what they were doing.
And these are basically just
like single slices like this.
So this is what
we would have been
learned as a frontend neuron.
So we take up each of the
neurons, and we just plot them.
And for plotting
this, we basically
take its Fourier transform
and then sort them
according to where the
center frequency is.
When we just saw the neurons
as to what they were learning
in the front end, we saw that
it is learning properties which
are very, very closely matching
with the traditional signal
processing.
So you would have something
like an onset detector learned
right here.
You're learning
windowing functions.
So in a way, it is learning
to have a kernel which
is best for a time frequency
representation for people who
have been using signal
processing, which
is like a Hamming
or Hanning window.
We are learning
these pure sinusoids,
which are responsible
for activating
a particular frequency.
So you can see the
richness as compared
to having a fixed, purely
sinusoidal basis function
right here.
So this was what we had done.
And then to share
the final thoughts,
I'll conclude by saying
that, OK, transformers
are proving to be a major
advancement in AI research
across the fields.
And it seems like they're
solving everything for now.
And hopefully, this
is not the end.
And we should keep an
eye out, and something
which would change and
have an impact which
is more than what
transformers have put.
And who knows what's
going to come next.
Yeah, so by that,
I'll just conclude.
And I'll be happy
to take questions.
Thank you, Prateek.
That was a really good talk.
And you provided some
really good insights
about how transformers
work on the audio case.
And yeah, thank you for that.
And now I would invite questions
from the class students.
Let me just stop the recording.